<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A tender salutation: or, loving epistle to such, who have a breathing in the innocent life of my friends with whom I walked in the outward observances. Also, for my relations (after the flesh) with all others professing God, and that have any breathings after the truth in the inward parts. Wherein something is declared in the power and light of God, concerning the sure foundation, and the house of God, with the inward glory, government, cloathing, feeding, non-superiority, and safety, that is in Gods habitation. With a word to the weak to establish them, that they faint not at the appearances of outward trouble for their consciences. - Whereunto is annexed a further discovery of God to my soul, concerning the spiritual temple, tabernacle and ark of Gods testimony, being the truth, life, and substance of the temple, tabernacle and ark of the testimony under the legal day. - To be read in the light, which discovers the things that be of God. -</title>
            <author>Chandler, Jacob.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1664</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 71 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A78561</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C1927A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R227552</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99895255</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99895255</idno>
            <idno type="VID">152621</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A78561)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 152621)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2309:9)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A tender salutation: or, loving epistle to such, who have a breathing in the innocent life of my friends with whom I walked in the outward observances. Also, for my relations (after the flesh) with all others professing God, and that have any breathings after the truth in the inward parts. Wherein something is declared in the power and light of God, concerning the sure foundation, and the house of God, with the inward glory, government, cloathing, feeding, non-superiority, and safety, that is in Gods habitation. With a word to the weak to establish them, that they faint not at the appearances of outward trouble for their consciences. - Whereunto is annexed a further discovery of God to my soul, concerning the spiritual temple, tabernacle and ark of Gods testimony, being the truth, life, and substance of the temple, tabernacle and ark of the testimony under the legal day. - To be read in the light, which discovers the things that be of God. -</title>
                  <author>Chandler, Jacob.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 30 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed in the year,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>M.DC.LXIV. [1664]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the William Andrews Clark Memorial Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Quakers --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Spiritual biography --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:152621:1"/>
            <p>A Tender Salutation: OR, <hi>LOVING EPISTLE</hi> To ſuch, who have a breathing in the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent life of my Friends, with whom I walked in the outward obſervances. ALSO For my Relations (after the fleſh) with all others profeſſing God, and that have any breathings after the Truth in the inward parts. WHEREIN Something is declared in the power and light of God, concerning the ſure Foundation, and the Houſe of God, with the inward Glory, Government, Cloathing, Feeding, Non-ſuperiori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and Safety, that is in Gods habitation. WITH A word to the Weak to eſtabliſh them, that they faint not at the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearances of outward Trouble for their Conſciences.— <hi>Whereunto is Annexed</hi> A Further diſcovery of God to my Soul, concerning the ſpiritual Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, Tabernacle and Ark of Gods Teſtimony, being the Truth, Life, and Subſtance of the Temple, Tabernacle and Ark of the Teſtimony under the Legal day. — To be read in the light, which diſcovers the things that be of God.— By <hi>Jacob Chandler.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>That which we have ſeen and heard (and felt) declare we unto you, that you might have fellowſhip with us: and truly our fellowſhip is with the Father, and with the Son Jeſus Chriſt, <bibl>
                  <hi>1 Joh. 1.3.</hi>
               </bibl>— If our earthly houſe of this Tabernacle were diſſolved, we have a houſe not made with hands, eternal in the heavens, <bibl>
                  <hi>2 Cor. 5.1.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>Printed in the Year, M.DC.LXIV.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb facs="tcp:152621:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:152621:2"/>
            <head>To all thoſe that love the Lord Jeſus in Power and Spirit, of my Friends, with whom I walked in the outward form: As well my profeſſing Relations (after the fleſh) with all elſe unto whom theſe preſents ſhall come, that have any breathings af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the precious Truth and life of God, Grace, Mercy and Peace be multiplied; the everlaſting love, life and truth of God dwell richly in you, &amp;c.</head>
            <p>DEar Friends, it has been oft upon me to write unto you of the things appertaining to the Kingdom of God in Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit and Truth: But my fleſh, with the reaſoning part, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood upon ſome conſiderations that now I'le forbear: But now after much ſtriving of the Lord God of Power, by his Spirit in my Soul, I am overcome with the overcomings of the love of God to write unto you: And this I find ſpringing up in me, to exhort you in tender bowels of love to look at the power, light, life and truth of God within, in every one of ye in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular; for Friends, its not the outward profeſſion that will ſtand you in ſtead in the day of Tryal, and in the day when all Secrets ſhall be made manifeſt, nor approve you to God, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the power and truth of God within: And therefore Friends in the bowels of tender compaſſions (let the evil minded think never ſo otherwiſe) I am moved (as before ſaid) to exhort you to look to your ſtanding, that you turn inward, and ſee what foundation you are built on; for Friends, that which is not built on a good foundation, will come to nothing, if the foundation be rotten and corrupt, you know whatſoever is built thereon ſuffers loſſe: Therefore let every ſoul take heed how he build thereon, for every mans works muſt be try'd. Now if you build on the truth and power of God, you build on a ſure foundation; but if you build on ſome other foundation, <hi>viz.</hi> ſome outward obſervation of external performances, out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward gifts, parts, humane wiſdom, or the ſayings of men,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:152621:3"/>though they may be good men, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Be it known unto you that its a falſe foundation, its deceivable, and the whole build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing will fall, great and lamentable will be the fall thereof: There is but one foundation for every poor ſoul that would be ſaved to build on, and another foundation can no man lay, than that which is already laid; and that is Jeſus Chriſt, the power of God, the wiſdom and truth of God: This is that ground and pillar of truth, that ſaves to the utmoſt all that come unto it, and build on it: Therefore Friends mind whether you have built on this foundation; whether the truth, power and Spirit of God be the thing that you mind, the foundation that you build on.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>How to come to the foundation, and build thereon; and how to know in the light of God, when the ſoul has built on the ſure foundation.</head>
               <p>THere muſt be a digging deep to build on this foundation, its not ſo eaſie as many Profeſſors think of; thou muſt dig down into thy innermoſt parts, into the ſecrets of thy ſoul deep, yea, very deep into humility muſt thou ſink and reſign up freely, and muſt be content to be nothing in thy will, wiſdom, underſtanding, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Oh ſoul, before thou canſt find the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation, the Rock to build on, and in the deep thou maiſt find it; for 'tis hid from the carnal wiſe man, by all his wiſdom he cannot ſearch it out, and all his notional knowledge (though he may ſpeak much of the foundation) is too ſhort to fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thom it.</p>
               <p>And now Friends, if you are built on this foundation, this Rock, then you are immovable, and cannot be ſhaken away from the confidence that you have ſpringing up from hence; and you are ſure and ſtedfaſt, and you walk in the pure fear of the Lord; and you are of tender bowels, and full of compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to all the Lords little ones; and you are of a meek ſpirit, and lowly in heart; and you are of tender compaſſion to all the Creation of God; you are weak with the weak, and bear a
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:152621:3"/>dear ſympathy with the afflicted precious ſons and daughters of <hi>Sion</hi> (let them be under what name and notion ſoever) if thou ſeeſt they are built on the power, life and truth of God, by which they breath after the everlaſting well-ſprings of life, the fountain of eternal love; thou haſt a principle in thee, if thou art upon the ſure foundation, that is ſtirred up with an endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>redneſſe to ſuch a breathing ſoul after the pure life of God; for my Friends, if we have built on a good foundation, then 'tis certain we have a good building; if we have a good Root, we have a good Tree; and if a good Tree, there muſt be good fruit: Now Friends, by this you may come to know whether you are built upon the power, life, and truth of God, or what foundation you are built on. Let me lay it farther before you.</p>
               <p>NOW if we have a good foundation, we have a good building, a good houſe, and there is good order and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment in this houſe, and good dyet, good meat and drink, and choice cloathing, and bleſſed ſafety, and no Lordly or Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſtick ſuperiority over one another in this houſe or family, that is built on the power and life of God, with other good things.</p>
               <p>Now that ſoul that hath built upon Chriſt the truth, and pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of God, hath a good building, a good houſe, and its none o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther but the houſe of God, the Temple of God, and God hath ſaid I'le dwell with you, and walk in you, and be your God <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And this every Saint is in particular, the habitation of God through the Spirit; this houſe is erected by the finger and pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of <hi>Jehovah Tzebaot,</hi> the Lord of Hoaſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The inward pure Government and ſhining glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and requirings in the houſe or habita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of God in the Spirit.</head>
               <p>AND farther Friends, this houſe of God has good go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, for its the Lord Jeſus that rules and governs in this houſe, and no other has right to govern but himſelf, for
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:152621:4"/>its his own, and hath bought it, and purchaſed it, not with corruptible things, as ſilver and gold, but with incorruptible, even with his own precious blood. Friends, when Chriſt is born in the ſoul of any, whether Jew or Gentile, bond or free, the government is put upon his ſhoulder, and to that end is this Son given, and the Child born, <hi>viz.</hi> that the government may be upon his ſhoulder, that he might rule and govern, and raign in the ſoul, in his own houſe, and he will raign in righre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe, and governs with pure Laws of light and freedom, not with Laws of darkneſſe and bondage: The pure and everlaſting God layes not hard ſervice upon his children and ſervants, he impoſes no heavy task upon his family, but what is in the pure freedom of the Spirit; his requirings are according to the growth of his children and ſervants, were it not, there would be diſorder inſtead of order; but no, no, my Friends, there is nothing but pure order in the houſe of God. The ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleſſed God rules, governs, and orders all in pure love, pure light, pure fear (taught by himſelf, and not by the precepts of men) pure righteouſneſſe, pure truth, and all inward: Now to ſee a Saint walk, and acting without, from theſe pure Laws of God within, oh what a great ſhine and glory does it caſt upon all it does! oh then! if ſo great a ſhine without, how great is that glory within? it being all glorious! it being that more excellent glory! it being the brightneſſe of the Fathers glory. Oh Friends, my ſoul admires this glory!</p>
               <p>Friends, ſink down from all your ſelfneſſe and ſomething<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and come into this moſt excellent glory, and lie with my ſoul ſtill from ſelf-acting before this glorious God, that this glory may paſſe beſore us, <hi>i. e.</hi> that it might more and more manifeſt its ſelf unto us, that we may come to be transformed from glory to glory by the pure Spirit of the living God: Now Friends, to ſee an houſe in ſuch an order, under ſuch a govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, is to ſee it in a comely order, to ſee it all fait, and to have no ſpot in it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:152621:4"/>
               <head>Of the heavenly bread and waters of life that is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided, eat and drank of, in the family and houſe of God, in the Spirit of the living God.</head>
               <p>THere is not only Rule in this houſe, but there is plentiful ſpiritual proviſion made for the whole family of God, and duly adminiſtred by the hand of living power and vertue, whereby it gives living ſpiritual nouriſhment for growth, to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe with the encreaſe of God; the eternal pure God gives it the bread of life, and the waters of life to eat of, and to drink of, and the ſoul being in a living ſtate, eats and drinks thereof, and is refreſhed, and cryes out evermore, Father give me of this bread of life, and theſe waters of life. Oh my ſoul, though the e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ternal grace of God have an internal, or inward caſte hereof, and it cryes and breaths in the pure fear and Spirit of God after more; and I find its not that I might eat and drink hereof alone, but that all might come in the fear of the living God to eat and drink hereof alſo with my ſoul, that we might rejoyce together in the Spirit, and that we might ſing a Hymn and ſpiritual Song, ſinging and making melody in out hearts to the living and pure fountain of life, giving pure and ſpiritual thanks alwayes to God, in the name, <hi>i. e.</hi> power and Spirit of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
               <p>Oh Friends, every ſoul that is ſurely fixed on this foundation of God, which alwayes ſtands ſure, have a meaſure of this heavenly food, <hi>viz.</hi> of this bread of life, and waters of life, dealt forth unto him according to his growth and appetite that his ſoul hath: Now we ought, and its our duty to be thankful with, or for ſuch a meaſure that we have, and to eat and drink to the glory of God. Friends, if it hold true in the outward, much more for the inward: But Friends, inlarge your appetite, open your mouth wide, and the Lord will fill it. Labour for a greater hunger and thirſt after this true bread and water of life, and you ſhall be filled, ſatisfied, and refreſhed. Oh Friends, thirſt not, hunger not ſo much after the outward obſervance,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:152621:5"/>which is a ſpending your money for that which is not bread, and your labour for that which ſatisfies not, and your ſtrength and time for that which periſhes: But labour to feed more of this true bread that cometh down from God out of heaven, the which whoſoever eats of is bleſſed; and to drink of thoſe wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters that runs by the Throne of God, whoſe ſtreams make glad the heart of the City, the habitation, the houſe of God; here Friends, does my ſoul come to experience what is meant by eating of the fruit of the Tree of life that <hi>John</hi> declared of, <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.7.</p>
               <p>And here I come to underſtand, know, feel, and to eat of the hidden Manna, that is ſpoke of in <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.17. its Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na that is hid from the wiſe and prudent of this world, but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed to them that fear, and love the pure God in Spirit and truth, and ſuch eats thereof to their ſouls nouriſhing and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſhing.</p>
               <p>Here my ſoul comes truly to eat of the fleſh, and to drink of the blood of the Lord Jeſus, and ſo comes to have life in it, for this is meat (or nouriſhment) indeed, and this is drink, (or refreſhment) indeed: I may eat long enough of the ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentary things, before my ſoul is nouriſhed and refreſhed in the eternal life; but if my ſoul eats and drinks of this ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual food, then my ſoul comes to have life and refreſhment, as my ſoul knows right well through the Spirit. Now in eating and drinking of the true bread, and water of life, we come to have communion with the body, and with the blood of Chriſt; for this communion is in the Spirit, and not in the letter, whoſe praiſe is of God, and not of men; for men are carnal, and this is ſpiritual: But this I know will ſeem ſtrange to a formal perſon, but let it, its true and faithful; yea, and our communion as Saints is in the Spirit, in eating this ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual bread and wine of the Kingdom of God, and not in the outward viſible elementary things; in the pure Spirit, is our pure communion; and our living communion in, and by the living Spirit.</p>
               <p>Here I come to know what it is to eat of the Supper of the Lord, amd to drink of the new Wine in the Fathers Kingdom. Now Friends I am not a judging of any of you, neither a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwading
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:152621:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>you (though the evil mind in ſome, may think I do in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſinuate to draw) from the uſe of the Elements, but do as the Lord ſhall direct you, and as you ſee him going before you in all you do, and moving you after, and leave nothing undone that you are really perſwaded in your Conſciences to be your duty, leſt you get a wound to your ſoul, and the Lord ſhould ſay, Who hath required this of you? &amp;c. But know from the Lord God, your life lies not here, <hi>viz.</hi> in theſe outward ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervations, though never ſo ſtrictly obſerved, but in God; and the communion of Saints lies not here, but in Spirit, truth and power, and therefore be not fierce againſt your Brethren that are not of your mind or perſwaſion in the outward obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation.</p>
               <p>Friends, turn in, and ſtand ſtill from your own wayes, and commune with your hearts, and make enquiry, Do I eat of this bread of life, and drink of thoſe pure ſprings of refreſhment? Does the Lord lead me into his green and freſh paſtures, and make me to lie down, and repoſe my ſoul in eternal kindneſſe: And do I receive my refreſhing from the pure, and clear chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtal fountain of living waters? Or do I take up in the outward obſervances, and leſſe mind this inward feeding, this inward drinking of the bread and waters of life? Oh Friends, this thing is to be well minded and weighed, in the truth and equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of God.</p>
               <p>Now there be many a poor ſoul more a minding the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward obſervances, than the inward vertue and power of the living God; as it was in dayes of old, ſo 'tis now, one cryes in this obſervation, Lo, here is Chriſt, and others in that obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, Lo, there is Chriſt, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Every perſwaſion cryes up their own, and ſayes, Come amongſt us, Chriſt is here, in the obſerving of this order, and others in that order, and ſo are divided amongſt themſelves, and are in confuſion, in <hi>Babylon,</hi> and knows not where Chriſt is; but what ſaith the Scripture, <hi>Believe them not, go not forth after them.</hi> Now Friends, Chriſt is nigh thee in thy heart, as <hi>Paul</hi> did witneſſe, <hi>The righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe that is of fatth, ſaith on this wiſe, Who ſhall aſcond to hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, to fetch Chriſt down? or who ſhall deſcend, to fetch Chriſt up;</hi> but what ſaith it, <hi>Chriſt is nigh then in thy heart,</hi> Rom. 10.6, 7, 8.</p>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:152621:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>Therefore Friends look not ſo much at the outward obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for Chriſt, if that be it, thou art in good earneſt deſirous to have, as to a looking in for Chriſt, for Chriſt, as before ſaid, is within, he is nigh in thy heart. Chriſt is the pearl of price, that great treaſure, that is hid in the field of every mans heart, and therefore Friends ſtand ſtill, from thy own words, works, thoughts, and carnal reaſonings of the fleſhly wiſe part, and hearken to the voyce of Chriſt in thy own particular, which cannot be heard, but in a ſtill, quiet ſtate of the ſoul, freely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned up to God, to be no more any thing in it ſelf, but that God might be all in all, and above all to its ſoul: And as to the outward (which man, fleſh and carnal wiſdom make ſuch a ſtir about) they walk in as they have freedom, and ſeeing the Lord going before them in it; and if any thing outward be done otherwiſe, its but fleſhly labour, which profits not.</p>
               <p>Oh but how many poor hearts is there that thinks God can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be enjoyed truly, and have communion with truly, but it muſt be injoyed and had in ſuch a way, in ſuch a form, which I know is the language of men in different forms, wayes, or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſions, every one binding as it were, and limiting the holy God to their perſwaſion, but Friends, the Lord is free to work where he pleaſe, and when he pleaſe, and on whom he pleaſe; and this I have heard ſome ſay, but will not ſtand unto it, but bind up the Lord in his workings (as much as they can) and calls all into queſtion, that the ſoul injoyes of God, if it come not in at their door (though it do come in at the door of the ſheepfold) as I have had experience of, and do know of what I ſpeak (and much more than this alſo.)</p>
               <p>But Friends, the Kingdom of heaven manifeſts its ſelf not in this, or that obſervation, but in righteouſneſſe, in power, Spirit and truth (and this will be owned by many in words, but denied in works, and ſo manifeſt that they are in <hi>Babilon,</hi> in confuſion) its he in what Narion ſoever, whether Jew or Gentile, bond or free, one or tother, that feareth the Lord, and worketh righteouſneſs, and that has all his works within wrought in and by God within, is excepted of him; its not he that ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves obſervations without, but he that ſtands in the power, Spirit, and truth of God within that is accepted, its not thus
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:152621:6"/>much outward obſervance, but this inward obedience.</p>
               <p>That ſoul that is convinced of this, is near the Kingdom, near the poſſeſſion; now ſtand but ſtill from acting in thy will, and ſink down into God, and ſettle upon the foundation, and reſign up all to the Lord, and ſtand to his order, and cleave to truth with a purpoſe of heart, and a little while (<hi>viz.</hi> the Lords time) he that ſhall come, will come, and bring thee in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Kingdom, into the poſſeſſion wherein thou ſhale enjoy all as before ſaid, and much more abundantly than I can ſpeak of; for I have but a ſtammering tongue in theſe matters, yet what the eternal God has freely given to me to experience; and to ſpring up in me freely declare I unto you my dear Friends all unto whom this is writ, that you might all eat hereof, and drink hereof, <hi>i. e.</hi> of that which this points unto, and ſo come to a higher growth in the birth of God, though I may be tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced, calumniated, and perſecuted one way or other, either in ſecret ſmilings or open reproaches by ſome or other; for I ſee in the light of God, and through the revelation of the Spirit, that the evil thing in ſome cannot bear, that the power, life, and truth of God ſhould clearly ſhine (though in words they may ſpeak otherwiſe) that they might go undiſcovered, but may ſeek to deſtroy this holy Child Jeſus, the birth of God, the ſhinings forth of the light of God, by putting upon it ſome falſe gloſſe, as deluſion, falſe light, hereſie, blaſphemie, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> as they did by Chriſt himſelf, and the ſervants of God in dayes paſt, and ſo oppoſing of the ſeed of God, and ſo as <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> will labour to deal ſubtilly, that it ſpread no further; but I ſhall leave it, and my ſelf to the Lord, and wait on him, as being given up to his will, not fearing what man can do or ſay, know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that I am a diſcharging my duty and conſcience herein.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of the inward adorning, and beautifying of Gods Houſe.</head>
               <p>FUrther Friends, the Lord my God will cloath you all with rich and ſoft cloathing, for all his Family is arrayed with ſoft Rayment: Oh every one that will be a Daughter of this King <hi>(Jehovah Tzebaot)</hi> the Lord of Hoaſt ſhall be all glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious within, and ſhall be brought into the Palace of the King,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:152621:7"/>and the King ſhall greatly delight in her beauty, for he is the Lord her God, and ſhe muſt worſhip him, and that in Spirit and in truth: I ſay, my Friends, God ſhall cloath, and has in a meaſure cloathed all his children with ſoft and fine Rayment: Are not they that wear ſoft Rayment in Kings houſes? yea, (my Friends) they are. Now, this ſoft Rayment I declare of, is the inward righteouſneſſe of the Lord Jeſus, which is the righteouſneſſe of all Gods Saints; this is the cloathing of our houſe from heaven that every Saint groans for, according to the meaſure of working; here's the putting on the Lord Jeſus in Spirit, power and truth; and this is that righteouſneſſe that juſtifies the ſoul to God, and is made acceptable to God, and to the Lamb. Friends, this Rayment I ſay is ſoft Rayment, its meek, ſtill and quiet, 'tis all in the Spirit, which Rayment, in the ſight of God, is of great price, of great value, of great eſteem. Oh Friends! There be many that have a covering, but not of my Spirit, ſaith the Lord. They have, I ſay, a cover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, ſomething in imitation of this I declare of; but its too narrow then that the ſoul can wrap its ſelf in it, ſo that its na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe is ſeen by a ſpiritual diſcerning: And therefore Friends all take heed, leſt you cover with ſuch a covering, inſomuch that your ſhame appears. I know there are ſome ſuch abroad, but they muſt ſtand or fall to their own Maſter, for every mans works muſt be tryed, and that by fire, <hi>viz.</hi> the fire of the pure living God, and if his works have not been wrought in God, and ſprung up from the foundation of the Apoſtles and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets (whoſe foundation was Chriſt Jeſus, the chief Corner ſtone that bore up all their building, and from which they reſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied that their works was wrought in God, and had it not) it muſt ſuffer loſſe.</p>
               <p>Some think to ſhrow'd themſelves under ſuch a form, and ſuch a form, and ſuch an obſervation outwardly; but its not the form, or obſervation outwardly, that can hide any poor ſoul from the wrath of God, and of the Lamb, the which every ſoul is expoſed to, let them be ſhrowded where they will; its no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but this covering, to wit, the inward righteouſneſſe of God, and Chriſt inveſting the ſoul, that hides from the wrath of the Lamb. This ſoft Rayment I declare unto you, is that
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:152621:7"/>Rayment with which the Bride, the Lambs wife makes her ſelf ready withall, and is ſo dreſſed therewith as a Bride is for her husband, in the choice embraces of everlaſting kindneſs; and this Rayment every foul muſt have on to come to the Marriage-ſupper withall, elſe its an unwelcome gueſt; though ſuch as have it not on them, may preſent themſelves amongſt the ſons and daughters of God, yet when the ſearcher of hearts, the everlaſting God, ſhall make inquiſition, then they ſhall be diſcovered to be but intruders, and though they held the form, they did not hold the head, by which all the members by joints and bands are knit together, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And though they had the ſemblance, the vizard, the ſhew of holineſſe, yet they denied the power, the inward life of purity and righteouſneſſe, and built on their form. The Lord ſayes to ſuch, what haſt thou to do to take my Name into thy mouth, ſeeing thou hateſt to be reformed; for he that nameth the Name of the Lord, muſt depart from iniquity; in vain is it that thou nameſt the Name of the Lord, in vain is the multitude of thy ſervices, the Lord will ſay, and does now ſay, Who hath required this at your hands? in vain is your ſolemn Aſſemblies, your Sabbaths, your Faſtings, Thankſgivings, Preaching, Praying, Supper, Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptiſme, Alms, Conference, with a multitude more, they are all an abomination to the Lord in the outward obſervation, becauſe thou haſt not on this wedding garment, this inward pure righteouſneſſe of the Lamb; and therefore they are an abomination, oh ſoul, becauſe performed, and externally carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on, out of the life, acted and carry'd on by the ſame ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit that thou ſinneſt with; ſure! this is a loathing to the pure, holy God of life, who rejoyces in truth in the inward parts from whence all without muſt ſpring; and not to take up an imitation from the Apoſtles practice, and to do ſuch works as thou gathereſt from the Scriptures (the writings of thoſe ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly men) out of that life that moved them to it, and many things elſe, which, oh ſoul! thou art ready to deſpiſe; but do thou wait upon the Lord for the more clearer breaking in of his light, and movings of his life, in thy own ſoul, and abide in his counſel, and abide his reproof, in thy ſoul, and be ſtill, look not forth, but mind thy watch within, leaſt the enemy of thy
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:152621:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſoul get an advantage againſt thee, and cleave to his power which thou ſhalt feel ſpring up (whereby thou ſhalt be able to overcome ſin, hell, death, wrath, ſelf condemnation, the world, and all evil, and thou ſhalt mount up in the life of God, and here ſhalt thou be cleathed with his righte ouſneſſe, and hear his voyce, and obey his Commandments in thy own particular, whoſe Commands are not grievous [to the Spirit] but joy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, ſo thou ſhalt have the light of life in thy own heart, as the Apoſtles and ſervants of God had before the Apoſtaſie, which was by them ſpoke of, 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2. the which came upon the world in ſome few years after the Apoſtles, but now in theſe latter dayes the light is dawned, and the Lord has viſited ſome with his tender mercies; the day-ſpring from on high hath viſited ſome, and God is a renewing of that defaced image that <hi>Adam</hi> had in innocercy, and that the Apoſtles had, by which they acted, and was led and guided into the wayes of purity and righteouſneſſe, doing what they did without, as they had a command from this innocent life in themſelves, with ſingleneſſe of heart, and great joy, bleſſing, prayſing, magnify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Lord God of power and purity; and this is that life that my ſoul in a meaſure feels, and has communion with.</p>
               <p>And my ſoul breaths to the everlaſting pure life, that thou maiſt have the ſame holy, pure, and innocent life, that the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles and Servants of God had, and now ſome in a meaſure have, in which life thou ſhalt learn what is the living ſenſe of the Scriptures, and Writings of holy men, and of thoſe Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances that the Apoſtles in their days was by the life command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to do, the which thou maiſt alſo do, or forbear, as the ſame life commands thee; though this the carnal and fleſhly reaſon cannot bear, but I may not ſpeak to pleaſe that, the Lord God everlaſting deſtroy, cut up, and conſume carnal wiſdom, fleſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly reaſon, and fleſhly will, by thy Almighty power, that they might never more hinder and deface thy pure, holy, glorious Image, and breakings forth of thy innocent breath, and of the pure and holy openings of thy indeared and tender love un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to it.</p>
               <p>And Friends, in this life you ſhall be cloathed with this pure, fine white linnen, <hi>John</hi> declared of, which is clean and white,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:152621:8"/>the which the Bride, the Lambs wife, is to bedeck her ſelf with for the Marriage with the Lamb; and therefore if any ſoul-pretends a Marriage with the Lamb, and have not this fine white linnen, which is the righteouſneſſe of the Saints, he or them ſhall be dealt ſeverely with; he ſhall be taken by the Lord, and bound, caſt out, and his portion appointed with the Hypocrite, where ſhall be weeping and gnaſhing of teeth for ever: Such ſhall be for ever baniſhed from the preſence of the Lord, and from the glory of his power, to be puniſhed with everlaſting deſtruction, becauſe they obeyed not the Lord, who commanded them to put on this garment, this righteouſneſſe, which is the Lord Jeſus in Spirit and truth; and becauſe they obeyed not, therefore ſudden deſtruction ſhall overtake them.</p>
               <p>Therefore Friends all, be exhorted in the pure fear and dread of the Almighty God, to turn <hi>[in]</hi> and make inquiry into this pure, ſpotleſſe, matchleſſe, fine white-linnen, which is the righteouſneſſe of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, and of the Saints; and you may come to know it by its effects, for as it hath been al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready declared, that it's ſoft Rayment, ſo 'tis, it's ſoft, gentle, and quiet where it is, and it fills the ſoul with peace, paſſing the carnal underſtanding; the work of righteouſneſſe ſhall be peace, and the effect of righteouſneſſe, quietneſſe and aſſurance for ever: And this habitation of God where this ſoft cloath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing is to be felt, is a peaceable habitation, there is ſure dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings, and quiet reſting places. And Friends, this ornament beautifies the ſoul in the ſight of God, becauſe its the comeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of God, the beauty of God that is upon it; this ſoul worſhips God in the beauties of holineſſe, in the Spirit of pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er upon the Mountain of righteouſneſſe.</p>
               <p>And Friends, this garment does not make the ſoul proud, but humbles; though its glorious apparrel, yet it does not puffe up, but layes the ſoul low, it ſinks the ſoul deep into humility, and brings the ſoul into a free reſignation to God: This ſoul thinks not ſcorn to hear the voyce of the Lord out of the mouth of a Babe and Suckling, but is content, yea, joyes in the Spirit of the Lord, to ſee the life move in a deſpiſed inſtrument by the world and carnal wiſdom.</p>
               <p>But thoſe that have covered, but not of the Spirit of the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:152621:9"/>Lord, not of this righteouſneſſe, of this pure garment, they are proud, deſpiſers of them that are good, fierce and cruel to the Saints, betrayers of the Saints, and of one another, as their ſelf-intereſt lies, yet build upon a form of godlineſſe, but deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the power thereof, and will own little in reality, but what is in their form and way. Friends, be ſtill, and conſider theſe things, and examine your hearts, Know you not that this is ſet. And further Friends, I find from this inward adorning and beautifying my ſoul to God, and to the Lamb, a garment of praiſe ſpring up in me, which leads me forth in the pure fear of the Lord, to praiſe, magnifie, and adore the pure living God; and here I come to experience and to feel, what it is to ſing a Hymne, or ſpiritual Song unto the Lord God of life, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Lamb that ſits upon the Throne, ſinging praiſe and halle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lujah to the Lord God Omnipotent, becauſe he has taken to himſelf his great Rule and Raign, ſinging with grace in my heart, which heretofore I had heard the ſound of (and many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther things) the which now my ſoul feels the living vertue, power and ſpirit of: Oh Friends! labour to feel the living power of this, and of theſe things in your own ſouls, and then we ſhall rejoyce together, and ſing the Song of the Lamb, which none can ſing, but thoſe that are redeemed from the earth. <hi>i. e.</hi> from the earthly will, wiſdom and practice; for the carnal part has nothing to do herein, but the Spirit only.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The precious Laws of Government in Gods Houſe, and the choice Anointings and Teachings by the Spirit.</head>
               <p>AND further Friends, the houſe, the habitation of God through the Spirit (that I declare of) has precious Laws of Government and Rule in it, which before was hinted at, I am made willing in the power of God to ſpeak a little further of it: The Laws of Gods houſe are ſpiritual, as the houſe is in the Spirit; ſo are the Laws, its called the Law of the Spirit of life, and this ſame Law ruled and governed in Chriſt Jeſus, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.2. and ſo in a meaſure in all the ſons and daughters of God. This is the Law of the new Covenant, that Law that comes from God out of <hi>Sion;</hi> this Law is not in
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:152621:9"/>the letter, but in the Spirit; the letter is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> the Law is within: As God ſaid, <hi>I'le put my Laws in your mind, and write them in your hearts, and they ſhall not teach every man his neighbour,</hi> ſaying, <hi>Know the Lord for all</hi> (in whoſe heart this Law ſhall be made manifeſt) <hi>ſhall know me from the leaſt, to the greateſt.</hi> Every one in particular as they come to have the ſeed of God, the Lamb of God, the life of God to riſe in them, they come to experience and feel this Law in the Spirit and life, teaching, directing, counſelling, and guiding into all truth, and as every particular comes to obey, they come to have peace with God, they ſhall be all taught of the Lord, and great ſhall be their peace. This peace paſſes all underſtanding, and its ſuch peace that none can ſpeak but the eternal God, nor can give but himſelf, who is the God of peace, God bleſſed for ever. And therefore Friends, every one of you turn in, and look for the Law in your hearts, in your minds, to be guided by it; and as you come to ſee it, and to be taught by it, obey it, and give up your minds to be guided by it, which will guide from ſin, Iniquity and tranſgreſſion; from the world, the pride of it, the faſhions of it, the luſt of it, and it will guide you into righteouſneſs, into life and peace with the eternal God. Friends, think not this manner of ſpeech ſtrange and contemptible, I know, in the ſpiritual knowing part, whereof I do affirm, and have had an inward feeling abundantly whereof I declare. Spend not all your precious time in the Law of the letter, written on paper with pen and ink, without the Law in the Spirit, written in your hearts by the Spirit of the living God. Oh Friends! what if you ſhould never ſo much ſtudy the letter, ſearch the letter, improve in the notions of the letter, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> If you are for all this ſtrangers to that Spirit that gave forth the letter at firſt, and unto which the letter points and directs to, that your life may not ſtand in a ſeeming outward conformity to the let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter without, but that your life may ſtand and abide in the Spirit within: This is that Law of [life] that is in the habitation of God, that is pure and perfect converting the ſoul. inlightning the underſtanding, whereby we may come to know him that is true, even Chriſt Jeſus, the true God and eternal life. Friends, this Law that every particular ſoul (that is become Gods houſe)
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:152621:10"/>is guided by, is not that Law from Mount <hi>Sinai,</hi> but from Mount <hi>Sion:</hi> Not from Mount <hi>Horeb,</hi> on which <hi>Moſes</hi> received the Law of the Ten Commandments, and writ it on Tables of ſtone, but the Law of the Spirit of the living God, written up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Tables of our hearts; neither is it that Law written by pen and ink without, but that written by the Spirit of the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving God within, and that muſt needs be a living Law, that a living Spirit writes.</p>
               <p>FRiends, look in for this living Law of the Spirit of life, for every one of ye have a meaſure thereof in your ſelves, now ſee that you be guided by it, and take not up in the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward thing, but preſſe through, and come to the Spirit and life, that your ſtanding (in this day) may be ſure and unſhaken, by all the powers of the evil One; that your joy may ſo abound, ſpringing from the true foundation, as that perſecution, tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, impriſonment, baniſhment, nor death it ſelf, may be able to take that Crown from you, nor in the leaſt may amaze, amuſe, or diſtract you from pure joy of the Lord, and from the obeying of the pure movings of the life in your ſouls.</p>
               <p>My ſoul knows ſomething of the inward feeling of this joy, but its unſpeakable, yet glorious; and as my ſoul comes to obey the inward teachings of the pure eternal God, ſo I come to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience, to feel the flowing in, and ſhedding abroad of this bleſſed peace of God in my heart; that Priſons, Baniſhment, Tribulation and Diſireſſe is even a light thing, through the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundance of love that my ſoul has to God (which is freely given unto me) becauſe then I can believe that my defence is the munition of Rocks, and that my bread ſhall be given me, and that my waters ſhall be ſure.</p>
               <p>Oh Friends! do ye all with my ſoul ſtand in the counſel of the everlaſting God, and reſign up freely to the Lord, body, ſoul, ſpirit, mind, and all things elſe, for he is faithful and able, yea, will keep that which is committed and reſigned up freely unto himſelf, who is <hi>El-ſhaddai</hi> the ſtrong and mighty God, and none ſhall be able to pull that out of his hands that is freely gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and reſigned to him according to his requiring. You have been often a ſpeaking after this manner, but come to the life,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:152621:10"/>to the truth, and ſtand in the power of it, the which you will never be able to do, unleſſe every one in particular abide in the counſel of the Lord, and hearken to his voyce, and hear his li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Word which is nigh, <hi>viz.</hi> in the heart of every particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar, which teaches every one to deny himſelf, <hi>viz.</hi> his ſelf-will, ſelf-wiſdom, ſelf-righteouſneſſe and underſtanding, and all that is ſelf; to be debaſed, laid low, thrown to the duſt, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come nothing, and what God would have him; of a rich man, rich in notions, in gifts, parts, and outward ſervices out of the life (as <hi>Paul</hi> before be was converted) to become poor in ſpirit; of a ſtrong man, to be made weak; of a proud man, to become humble, than a little child may lead him; of a no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional one, to be made ignorant, &amp;c. That now every parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular may be made new again, a living Temple and habitation of God to dwell in, and to reach them out of his Law as they are able to receive it from him; and as you come to be taught of the Lord, and to obey his teachings which are pure, ſo you ſhall come to be the bleſſed of the Lord, and the Word of the Lord ſhall dwell richly in you, and you ſhall become ſtrong in the power and Spirit of the Lord; the brother of low degree ſhall be exalted, as he abides in the anointings, and the igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant that has let go his knowledge in the knowing comprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, ſhall be inlightned; and as he waits upon the Lord, and hearkens to his teachings within, by the Law of the Spirit of life writ by the Spirit of the living God in his heart, he (I ſay) ſhall come to a good underſtanding in the miſteries of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of God, and ſhall know the doctrine that is of God, for who teaches to profit like him? Though others that feeds up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Tree of knowledge, and comprehends much in the knowing part, ſhall ſlight it, and call it ſtrange doctrine, delu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, hereſie, &amp;c. But why is it? becauſe they feed not on the Tree of life, but on the Tree of knowledge, which apart and ſeparate from the Tree of life, is death, deſtruction, and poyſon to the ſoul.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>No Lordly and Majeſtical Superiority in Gods houſe.</head>
               <p>AGain, There is no Superiority in the Family of God, the children of God are all equal, there is none allowed by
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:152621:11"/>the Father to be one above the other, to rule it, and Lord it over his Brothers Conſcience, as we ſee in the world by men that would fain be reputed ſomething, as to the matters of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs and fear of the Lord, when its not the fear of the Lord that puts them on to aſſume and arrogate to themſelves a pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er over their Brothers Conſcience, but its the fleſh, the Devil, and carnal wiſdom that puts them upon it: Too much of this ſpirit was in the Diſciples of old, but Chriſt rebuked them for it. The true children in the Family of God they ſerve one an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other, not uſurp over one another; its true God may and does, diſcover his ſecrets and myſteries of the Kingdom, more to ſome, than to others of his children; not that they ſhould lift up themſelves, above their Fellow-brethren, but that they ſhould ſubmit to the Brother of low degree, and ſtrengthen the weak hands, and feeble knees, and conſolate the diſcom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forted, with the overflowings of that Cup of bleſſing that God hath filled to him.</p>
               <p>But, ah, how does proud man! that has got into the form of godlineſſe, Lord it over them that he dreams are under him, and ſo demonſtrate they have an Antichriſtian ſpirit. Oh Friends! there is a quiet, peaceable, loving carriage in the children of God one towards the other, according to the anointing recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved; there's love not only in, word, but in deed, there's a ſweet condeſcending according to the requirings of God one to the other, a holy bearing and forbearing in this Family; there's not a ſhoving with the ſhoulder, and a puſhing one at the other, for that's of the fleſh, but a ſubmitting the ſhoulder to bear each others burthen they lay out for each others good, of what the eternal God has laid into their hearts, and all this according to his working in them, who works freely, that all might be ſtren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gthned and comforted; ſo that here's not among the children of God Superiority one over another, but all equally alike the children of God, and Brethren one of another.</p>
               <p>And certain I am, that according to the meaſure of Gods indwelling in the pure light of life in the ſoul, ſo, the haughti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of man is crucified, and laid low; for haughtineſſe and lordlineſſe of ſpirit is from the fleſh and beneath: But as the ſoul receives of the Spirit of light and life, and obeyes its
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:152621:11"/>teachings and drawings, it ſhall find it drawing him from this ſpirit of haughtineſſe and lordlineſſe, into a humble and low frame, that it can (ſtanding in the power of ſuch drawings) condeſcend to waſh his Brethrens feet, as Chriſt did, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come in the power of this ſo little and low, that a little Child may lead him (to wit) Chriſt the Babe of righteouſneſſe, the holy One of God; for Friends, the more the ſoul is anoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with the conſecrating oyle, <hi>i. e.</hi> the Spirit of God, the more humble that ſoul is, and willing to inſtruct his poor and weak Brother, what God has done for his ſoul in order for his weak Brothers perſeverance in the truth; ſuch a ſoul under the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nointing of God, is far from a Lordly and Majeſtical ſpirit: This is that which God deſtroyes in the day of his power, and glorious appearings of his life in a ſoul; <hi>In that day the lofty looks of man ſhall be humbled, and the hanghtineſſe of men ſhall be bowed down, and the Lord alone ſhall be exaleed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>AND now my dear Friends, Turn in, and ſee what you can experience in your own particulars, that your re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joycing may be in your ſelves, and not in another; and think not this ſtrange, that you are preſſed through ſuch a weak inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment as I am, to turn in, and to ſee if theſe things are wrought by the eternal Spirit, and that you have your teachings from the Spirit within.</p>
               <p>Conſider Friends, the ſoul that is to be ſaved is within, and Chriſt the light is within; he ſayes, <hi>I am meek and low in heart: And Chriſt in you the hope of glory: And know you not that Chriſt is in you, &amp;c.</hi> And the Law of the Spirit of life, by which every particular is taught (though every particular does not learn) holineſſe, righteouſneſſe, and the true fear of the Lord, &amp;c. is ſaid to be within: <hi>I'le put my Law in your minds, and write it in your hearts, &amp;c.</hi> And God himſelf is within, as the Apoſtle declaved, I <hi>will dwell in you, and walk in you, and you ſhall be my people, and I will be your God.</hi> Now if all this is within, then turn in and examine your ſelves, what of the teachings, what of the life, of the power and Spirit; what of the flowings forth of the living vertues of the eternal Fountain of righteouſneſſe do I feel ſpring up in me, that I,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:152621:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>and thou, oh ſoul, may rejoyce in our own portion, and not in anothers, and each of us come to ſit down under our own Vine in particular, and eat of the ſweet fruit hereof, none ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king afraid, ſayes my ſoul: This Vine to be Chriſt, and the Father to be the Husbandman, that we may rejoyce together as the children of one Father, all drinking into that one Rock, and baptized into one Spirit, and bound up together in the bundle of one life; and that our union, and communion, may ſtand in the life, Spirit and power, and not in forms and out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward obſervances, ſaith my ſoul.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A brief diſcovery of the entrance into this houſe and habitation of God.</head>
               <p>AND Friends, There is no entring into this houſe of God but by great travel and pains; Thou muſt travel out of <hi>Egypt</hi> through the loathſom Wilderneſte, to enter into <hi>Canaan;</hi> Thou muſt, oh ſoul, experience the bond of thy iniquities to be broken; Thou muſt know a day of trouble, of miſery, a day of burning, before thou canſt advance this Church that is in God; I ſay, Thou muſt know the terrors of the Lord, as my ſoul has known by reaſon of ſin; a day of ſhaking the foundations of the earth, and making it to tremble; a feeling the Arrows of the Almighty God ſtick in thy ſoul, and great diſquietneſſe with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in thy borders, becauſe ſin is in thy Tabernacle, thou muſt feel his indignation, as my ſoul hath (according to thy meaſure) and 'tis good to bear it, becauſe of ſin, untill he raiſe thee up, and comfort thy ſoul, as ſin is purged out.</p>
               <p>Wait upon the Lord, and ſuffer the wrath of God to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed from heaven againſt thy unrighteouſneſſe, and in due time thou ſhalt feel a power-ſpringing up from that light which firſt diſcover'd to thee thy ſin, whereby thou ſhalt have ſin caſt out, but not all at once, but as thou waiteſt here, and obeveſt, ſo thou ſhalt feel thy ſin, and thy old nature, and all ſelf deſtroyed and crucifyed, ſo thou ſhalt experience a crucifying with Chriſt, that thou maiſt live with him a pure, innocent and ſpotleſſe life; and as thy ſin and old nature, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> is deſtroyed, and dies, ſo ſhall Chriſt the light of life live in thee, and ſo as thou obeyeſt
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:152621:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>this light of life which is riſen to deſtroy thy death, thou ſhalt come to live in the pure life, and have it in your ſelves, and ſo, as he who is this light of life, to wit, Chriſt Jeſus, lives in you, you ſhall live alſo in him, and ſo come to experience what it is to dwell in the houſe of God, and to be a member of the true Church that is in God, and to experience all, and much more, as already declared.</p>
               <p>And now Friends, unto the Lord I commit you and give up to be taught, governed and guided by his pure Law of righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ou ſneſſe, the Law of the Spirit of life, which is the Law writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in the heart, which Law is pure, and conſents not to ſin, but reproves it, and manifeſts it, and holds out a power to mortifie it, the which every ſoul that waits on the Lord, and ſtands in his counſel, ſhall feel ſpring up, to caſt out the ſon of the bond-woman, for it ſhall not be heir with the ſon of the free-woman, <hi>i. e.</hi> with Chriſt, the life, and ſeed of God.</p>
               <p>And that you might be cloathed with the garment of light and ſalvation, and with zeal and holy courage for the Lord, as with a Cloak; and that you might come to praiſe and adore the living God of endleſſe life; and that you might be fed upon the Mountain of Gods holineſſe with the Feaſt that God has prepared, a Feaſt of fat things, of Wines well refined; and that he might deſtroy by the appearance of his life, the vail that is upon you, that you might come forth from darkneſſe, and walk more in the light of life.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A word to the Weak, to eſtabliſh and direct them, that they faint nat, at the ſight of the outward Adverſary in their Meetings.</head>
               <p>AND Friends, There is a deſire riſen in me, that every one of you in particular, may come ſo to be eſtabliſhed on that ſure foundation, the everlaſting Rock of Ages, that you may not be ſo ſoon ſhaken away (many of you) from the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence that you ſeem to have for God and Truth, as you are perſwaded: I ſpeak not this to reproach you, but in the power of God to eſtabliſh you: Friends, your <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> going forth out of the power of God, into the fleſh, is it that makes you faint in
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:152621:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>the day of adverſity, and in the face of your enemy.</p>
               <p>Therefore Friends, if you would be valiant for the truth, mind the life of God in your ſouls, reſide and dwell in it, and give up all unto it; fix your mind ſteddy upon it, and ſtay thereon; and as thou comes to this (O ſoul) thou ſhalt be kept in peace and quiet, off from the trouble and diſquiet that the fleſh raiſes up; for God will keep him in perfect peace, whoſe mind is ſtaid upon him.</p>
               <p>Friends, it ill becomes thoſe that fears the Lord, to be of ſuch a fearful, frightful ſpirit, as I have obſerved there is ſometimes in your Meetings, though it be but of ſuſpition of an invaſion by the enemy without: Friends, the deſire in my ſoul is, that you would mind the life, the ſpirit in you, and be ſtill and quiet in the patience of the life and Lamb of God, according to the meaſure in you; and as you mind this, and dwell in this, your fears and terrors of the fleſh will abate, and your courage advance; for the life of the pure God crucifies the fleſh, which leads to death.</p>
               <p>The Spirit of God is a Spirit of love, and of a ſound mind, it caſts out ſuch fear, and it is not a Spirit of ſlaviſh fear, ſo that (my Friends) if you be the ſons and daught<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of God, why then you are led by the Spirit, and not by the fleſh, which is fearful, ſinful, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And if you have the Spirit, and live in the Spirit, why then it has mortified the deeds of the fleſh, which are evil, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> See <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.5. to the 17. <hi>verſe. They which are after the fleſh, do mind the things of the fleſh; and they that are after the Spirit, the things of the Spirit.</hi> Slaviſh fear and cowardiſe for truth is of the fleſh, and to be fleſhly and carnally minded is death to the ſoul; but to be ſpiritually minded is life.</p>
               <p>Oh Friends, it has been a trouble to my ſpirit ſometimes to ſee the diſtraction, perturbation and trouble that many have entered into in their Meetings at a ſhallow, &amp;c. Oh Friends, labor to crucifie this old man with his fleſhly mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers and branches that ſprings forth into the viſible life, and what you have in the inviſible life, watch to have it ſtren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gthned, and live in the meaſure you have attained of this inviſible or inward life in your own particulars.</p>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:152621:13"/>
               <p>And if any further of the coming in of the viſible ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my be into your Meetings (in the diſcharging what you are perſwaded to be your duty) which is too probable and likely;) be ſtill and quiet in your ſelves, ſweetly compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, with your mind fixed upon God, enjoying communion in the life and Spirit of God, according to your particular meaſure, keeping ſteddy in the beholdings of the life, and be in the ſerious purſuit of it, and do not ſuffer your thoughts and your minds to ſtraggle in the leaſt, no not for a moment, though the enemy provoke you; be diligent in the watch, that the enemy of your ſoul, the inviſible ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my break not in to overthrow your peace and communion with God, and deſtroy your purſuit in the life, and ſo your peace being loſt, your watch down, and the enemy broke in, then you enter into the fleſh in the troubles, fears, tempeſts and diſquiets which the life is freed from, &amp;c. and ſo will be ready to ſay any thing, do any thing, ſo that you might be acquitted of the enemy without, and releaſed of a Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and baniſhment for thy body, which affrights many poor hearts, who conſiders not the Priſon, the baniſhment, and darkneſſe and trouble that their ſouls is in, in the want of the light, life, Spirit, peace and communion with God.</p>
               <p>Oh Friends, I ſay unto you all watch! watch the life, and go not from upon any terms; be ſurely built on the ſure foundation, and you ſhall be able to ſay in the ſame life (ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to thy meaſure) as <hi>David, I am fixed, I am fixed, O God I am fixed:</hi> O happy ſtate! here is the only ſafety.</p>
               <p>And now unto the Lord (once more) I commit you, that every one of you may ſo come to be eſtabliſhed on that ſure foundation the everlaſting Rock of Ages, and build ſo up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the power and life of God, that Priſons, Fines, Perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, the gates of hell, even death it ſelf may not prevail againſt you, non affright you. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:152621:14"/>
               <head>Some further diſcovery of Gods houſe or habitation through the Spirit; And, according to my meaſure, declaring of the ſpiritual Temple or Tabernacle, and Ark of the Teſtimony; the Truth, Life and Subſtance of the Temple or Tabernacle, and Ark of the Teſtimony under the Legal diſpenſation, to be read in the light, which manifeſls the things that are of God.</head>
               <p>FRiends, The houſe and habitation of God, is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the Temple or Tabernacle of God where God dwells, walks, moves, &amp;c. and this was ſhewed by the Temple under the Law, in which Temple or Tabernacle, God was graciouſly preſent with his people in that day, but now dwells no longer in Temples made with hands, but in his people and children, who are the Temple and hat itati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of God through the Spirit. Though, my Friends, ſome do imagine, that the Legal Temple or Tabernacle is a figure holding forth to us the outward Ordinances, <hi>viz.</hi> Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Praying, Supper, Water, Baptiſm, &amp;c. And ſome calls this a new Iemple ſtate (and 'tis to be feared there do a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bide, and look no further (or very little) higher than juſt to draw from it the outward obſervation) but God hath revealed it otherwiſe to me, and a neceſſity is laid upon me, being called to it, not to deny it. In order to your under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding of this, Conſider,</p>
               <p n="1">I. That in the Legal Temple was the Ark of the Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and this was the Ark of his preſence. Now this Ark figured forth the Lord Jeſus in the Spirit, which dwells in his people (or particularly in a Saint) this is the Ark of the New Teſtament,
<note place="margin">Iſa. 42.6. Mal. 3.1.</note> which alſo is called the New Covenant. That Ark was Legal, this is a Goſpel-Ark; that was an out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Ark, this an inward Ark; that was an Ark in a form, this an Ark in the power; that was in a Type and ſhadow, this is in truth and in ſubſtance;
<note place="margin">Deut. 10.30.</note> that was wrought by
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:152621:14"/>mans hands, this is wrought by the finger and Spirit of God: I ſay, that Legal Ark was a Type,
<note place="margin">Hebr 9.3, 4. Exod. 23.33.</note> and Chriſt Jeſus the Ark of the New Covenant, is the Antitype of the Tipe; the reſidence of the Legal Ark was in the Temple or Taber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacle, not in the outward Court or Sanctuary, but within the Curtain or Vail, called the <hi>Holy of Holies</hi> by Gods ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment, ſo is the Goſpel-Ark, the Ark of the New Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, its in the holy place, its within the Vail,
<note place="margin">Col. 1.27.</note> its not in the outward Court of profeſſion, or Sanctuary of obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, but within; <hi>Chriſt in you the hopes of glory: And know you not that Chriſt is in you, except you be reprobates?</hi> 2 Cor. 13.5.</p>
               <p n="2">II. In this Legal Ark (whoſe place of reſidence (as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſaid) was in the Temple,
<note place="margin">Deut. 10.4, 5.</note> and in the holy of holies in the Temple) there was put the two Tables of ſtone, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on was the Law of the Ten Words, or Ten Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments by which the <hi>Jews</hi> in their day was to walk; what does this figure forth unto us,
<note place="margin">Rom. 8.2.</note> but the Law of the Spirit of life which was in Chriſt Jeſus, the Ark of Gods preſence, which Law is alwayes in the Ark for believers to walk by, as God ſaid, <hi>This is my Son, hear him.</hi> And Friends, its he only that teaches the will of God perfectly and profitably; for none teaches to profit like him.
<note place="margin">Hebr. 8.10. Jet 31.33. 2 Cor. 3 3.</note> 
                  <hi>I will write my Law in your hearts and put it into your inward parts, ſaid the Lord.</hi> Its not now, as under the Legal diſpenſation, a written Law without on Tables of ſtone, or by pen and ink, but upon the Tables of our hearts, by the Spirit of the living God; and this Law of the Spirit of life, is read and known by all that comes to know it in the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, the light, the Ark, the Covenant, and Goſpel of God.</p>
               <p n="3">III. In the Legal Ark there was <hi>Aarons</hi> Rod put, which budded in the Ark, &amp;c. what does this figure forth? <hi>Anſ.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Heb. 9.4. Gal. 5.22. John 15.8. John 3.21. Iſa. 26.12. Ezek. 37.1, &amp;c.</note> The Spirit of God, which buds, bloſſoms, and brings forth fruit to the praiſe and glory of the pure God, which pure Spirit is in Chriſt Jeſus the Ark of God, without which none can bring forth fruit, except they abide in it, and that in them, working the works of God in them, and for them; for without this <hi>Aarons</hi> Rod, <hi>viz.</hi> the Spirit of God,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:152621:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>what dry ſticks, dry bones are we? bringing forth no fruit to God, nor good to our Neighbour; ſo that to me <hi>Aarons</hi> Rod does figure forth the pure Spirit of life,
<note place="margin">Col. 1.27, 29.</note> and the budding is that fruit that is brought forth, where it is by its operation and work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and this is in the Ark, in Chriſt Jeſus, who dwells in the Temple that is made without hands, <hi>Acts</hi> 17.24. <hi>Chap.</hi> 7.48.</p>
               <p n="4">IV. In the Ark of the Legal Temple there was a golden pot of Manna put, &amp;c. Now what alſo does this figure forth? I ſhall declare as God hath inlightned me in it, and given my ſoul to taſte hereof, which is the ſweet fruit, and divine mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtations of his precious love to the ſoul in and through the Spirit, its the precious fruit of the Kingdom of light, the true bread that cometh down from heaven,
<note place="margin">John 6.51.</note> the which the ſoul that eats thereof ſhall never dye; and no ſoul comes to eat of this Manna but as he overcomes,
<note place="margin">Rev. 1 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>7.</note> and he that overcomes ſhall eat of this hidden Manna, <hi>i. e.</hi> ſhall eat of the peaceable fruits, and have the divine manifeſtations, and ſweet refreſhings of the eternal Spirit of truth. It was laid up in the golden pot; now gold is the pureſtand fineſt of all mettals;
<note place="margin">1 Tim. 3.9.</note> ſo this Manna I ſpeak of, is put into a clean Veſſel, into a pure and holy heart; and the more any ſoul comes to be clean, pure and holy, the more they come to enjoy and ſee God; <hi>For the pure in heart ſhall ſee God;
<note place="margin">Mat. 3.8. Heb. 11.14.</note> and without holineſſe none ſhall ſee God:</hi> But I ſay, as they come to be holy and pure, ſo they ſhall ſee God; and the more the ſoul comes to ſee God, the more is that ſoul tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed into the likeneſſe of God; now the more any ſoul ſees God, and is like God, the more does that ſoul eat of this hid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den Manna, <hi>i. e.</hi> this ſoul feels a ſpting of life, peace, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort,
<note place="margin">2 Cor 3.18.</note> joy in the Holy Ghoſt ſpring up in him, wherein the ſoul comes to be ſtrengthned, fixed and eſtabliſhed in God, and his ſoul feeds on this and is refreſhed; and this is the Manna, the meat he eats that the world knows not of, and which a carnal fleſh (in all its outward ſhew) cannot feel nor ſee,
<note place="margin">John 4.32.</note> for its ſpiritually ſeen and felt. Bleſſed is he that knows and feels the living vertue and ſpring of it.</p>
               <p n="5">V. Upon the Legal Ark there was the Mercy-ſeat, &amp;c. what does this ſhew? <hi>Anſw.</hi> It figures forth unto us, that the tender mercies of God is ſeated on Jeſus Chriſt; for God in himſelf
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:152621:15"/>is unknowable, unutterable, unexpreſſable, unconceivable, as having nothing to do with his creatures, or his creatures with him; but as he hath introduced himſelf into them through his Son, and ſo the eternal God comes to be known, ſeen, felt and heard, as he hath, and does make forth himſelf through his Son by his Spirit; ſo that all knowledge, and mercy of God comes in upon the revelation of the Son, as Chriſt ſaid,
<note place="margin">John 1.18. Mat. 11.27.</note> 
                  <hi>None have ſeen God at any time ſave the Son, and unto whom the Son ſhall reveal him:</hi> Neither can we ſee God in the divine mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtation and diſcovery in the Spirit of his eternal goodneſſe, righteouſneſſe and truth, except the Son does reveal him; ſo that in this brief hint it may be ſeen, if the light of God doth inlighten according to the meaſure of it, that its on the Ark of the teſtimony of God (to wit) Chriſt Jeſus, that mercy is ſeated; for this is the way of all mercy to the whole Creation. Friends, I give you but a hint of theſe things, though ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times I ſee much of theſe things in the deep.</p>
               <p n="6">VI. Upon the Legal Ark was two Cherubims, covering their faces with their wings becauſe of his preſence: Now as God manifeſts his living, pure preſence, the fleſh is hid, and doth diſappear; and that ſoul is led by the Spirit, and walks after the Spirit, and not after the fleſh.
<note place="margin">Rom. 8.1, 14.</note> Oh when the Lord God in his eternal Spirit of light, and holy brightneſſe appears, according to the meaſure of its manifeſtation, what a trembling is there in the fleſh by reaſon of his preſence and glorious brightneſſe that is ſhining in them,
<note place="margin">Mat 17.5, 6, 7, 8.</note> that is ſeen and felt in the light and life of God. Oh what a covering, hiding and vailing of the fleſh is there, as not being able to look upon, or behold ſuch bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of his glory. Friends, theſe things are true and faithful.</p>
               <p n="7">VII. The everlaſting God did promiſe to meet with his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple (in the Legal day) and to commune with them upon the Mercy-ſeat, &amp;c. Oh Friends? God in old times did ſpeak,
<note place="margin">Heb. 1.1, 2.</note> commune, and meet with his people in divers manners, and at ſundry times; but now in theſe laſt dayes he has, and does ſpeak, meet and commune with his people in, and by his Son,
<note place="margin">Mark 9.7.</note> who ſayes, <hi>This is my Son, hear him:</hi> And its he that has the mind and meſſage of the Father, and ſhews it his true Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples: He ſpeaks not of himſelf, but what he hears and receives
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:152621:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>of the Father that he declares;
<note place="margin">John 3.32. John 10.30. 1 John 2.23.</note> and here it is that the ſoul meets, and communes with the Father, becauſe he hath the Son; <hi>for the Father and the Son are one; and he that hath the Son, hath the Father alſo; and he that hath the Father, hath the Son alſo.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now as any ſoul comes to hear the voyce of the Son of God in themſelves particularly and comes to obey the voyce of the Son of God in themſelves, which obedience is life, comes to meet with the Father in the tender imbraces of divine love, ſeated in his tender mercies; but if the ſoul rebells, and diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beyes his heavenly voyce,
<note place="margin">Iſa. 63.10.</note> and vexes his holy Spirit, then the ſoul comes not to partake of this heavenly bleſſing (to wit) of this heavenly communication, and glorious making forth of the eternal preſence of the everlaſting God; but, I ſay, if the ſoul hears, and obeyes the voyce of the Son of God, as he obeys [ſo] he comes to have life; and becauſe he lives, whoſe voyce it is they obey, they ſhall live alſo; for, ſaid Chriſt, <hi>Becauſe I live, ye ſhall live alſo,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">John 14 19.</note> whoſe voyce is in the ſoul, calling to be pure, as God is pure; holy, as God is holy; and ſo to live in all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of holy converſation in the ſtreamings forth of the life within,
<note place="margin">1 Pet. 1.15.</note> whoſe voyce calls for a love to all righteouſneſſe, and to a hatred and forſaking of all iniquity though never ſo ſecret, whoſe voyce is for inward cleanſing, inward purifying: <hi>As be ye pure and clean that bear the Veſſels of the Lord.</hi> Now if we would be Veſſels holding the treaſures of heaven in us,
<note place="margin">2 Cor. 4.7.</note> if we would be Temples of the Holy Ghoſt, houſes and habitations of God through the Spirit, we muſt be pure, clean and holy; for Friends, <hi>Holineſſe becomes the houſe of the Lord for ever.</hi> Now this the voyce of Chriſt the Son of God calls for in us,
<note place="margin">Iſal. 93.5.</note> and as every ſoul comes to obey the voyce of the Son in the Spirit of power, he comes to meet and commune with the eternal God in his everlaſting mercies.</p>
               <p>Thus Friends, ye have a brief deſcription of what God has ſhew'd unto me though more ſometimes by the light of God I ſee in a great deep, for the which there is a deſire in me, to be found waiting on the everlaſting light, till he is pleaſed to bring it forth, and duly manifeſt it.</p>
               <p>Now how by Temple, Tabernacle, Ark, can be meant or un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:152621:16"/>outward Ordinances, as at the beginning was ſpoke of; and for ſuch that are come to this ſtate herein mentioned, and have no freedom to ſubſcribe to, and walk in, I know not; but I have a teſtimony in my ſoul, that the ſubſtance compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hends and includes all the ſhadows and ſigns (and ſigns are not for them that believe, but for them that believe not) ſo that if my ſoul enjoyes the ſubſtance, and lives in the poſſeſſion (ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the meaſure) the which I have an inward teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of, let who will queſtion it (the which ſome has done) then I have the end of all the ſhadows and ſigns;
<note place="margin">Col. 2.16, 17.</note> for they all end in Chriſt, who is the truth, ſubſtance (of all) light, life, power, Goſpel, Covenant, Word, Supper, Baptiſme, Reſt, &amp;c. ſo that in him my ſoul repoſes and finds reſt, and in his light can dilcern betwixt the ſhadow and the ſubſtance, the form and the power, the letter and the Spirit; not ſlighting that with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out, yet eſteeming more of that within; and walk in that with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out, as I find freedom within, and ſo my ſoul enjoyes peace,
<note place="margin">Iſa. 32.17.</note> for its peace God calls unto; and the effect of righteouſneſſe is peace, and that is righteous that God works; ſo unto what the righteous God works freedom to, therein let's obey; herein none ſhall be oppreſſed, and his Conſcience Lorded over, but walk in the freedom and liberty wherewith Chriſt does make free; only Brethren, uſe not your liberty for an occaſion to the fleſh, the which if you do pretend to liberty in Chriſt and walk carnally, you demonſtrate that you know not this liberty and freedom by Chriſt, but are in bondage to this day.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Judge not raſhly, leaſt you be judged; for with what raſh judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ye judge of, the ſame ſhall you be judged withall.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Wherefore holy Brethren, partakers of the heavenly calling, conſider the Apoſtle, and High Prieſt of our profeſſion Chriſt Jeſus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Who was faithful to him that appointed him, as alſo</hi> Moſes <hi>was faithful in all his houſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For this man was counted worthy of more glory than</hi> Moſes, <hi>and</hi> Moſes <hi>was faithful in all his houſe as a ſervant, for a teſtimony of thoſe things which were to be ſpoken after. But Chriſt as a Son over his own houſe, whoſe houſe are we, if we hold faſt the conſidence, and the rejoycing of the hope firm unto the end.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:152621:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Wherefore as the Holy Ghoſt ſaith, To day if you will hear his voyce, harden not your hearts, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>So I ſware in my wrath that they ſhall not enter into my reſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Becauſe I was grieved with that generation, and ſaid, They do alway erre in their hearts, and they have not known my wayes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Wherefore Brethren, Take heed, leaſt there be in any of you an evil heart of unbelief in departing from the living God,</hi> Hebr. 3.1, 2, 3, 5, 6, 7, 10 11, 12.</p>
               <p>Now unto <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> him who is able to keep you from falling, I commit you, and the peace of God that paſſeth all underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing fill you, and God everlaſting make you perfect, ſtrengthen, eſtabliſh, ſettle you, working in you that-which-is-well-pleaſing in his ſight, through Jeſus Chriſt, to whom be glory for ever, and for ever. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>
                     <date>Near the end of the 4th. Month, in the Year, 1664.</date>
                  </dateline>
                  <signed>Your Brother, That waits to ſee the redemption of the pure ſeed of God in you all; and its enlargement over all the Earth. <hi>J. C.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:152621:17"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
